New York Metro Area Postal Union Records WAG.103
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Metro Area Postal Union Records
1910-1980s
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Metro Area Postal Union
WAG.103
80 Linear Feet (80 boxes)
Historical/Biographical Note
The New York Metro Area Postal Union (American Postal Workers Union, Local 10) represents clerks, motor vehicle staff, maintenance workers and mail-handlers in the great New York City area. (Some mail-handlers, however, are represented by other unions.) By the 1980s the local enrolled more than 25,000 members. The local originated as Local 10 of the National Federation of Post Office Clerks. Officers and most of the members of this local seceded in 1958 to become the Postal Union of Manhattan-Bronx Clerks (later the Manhattan-Bronx Postal Union), with the aim of uniting many postal crafts in one industrial union. The local became part of the newly created American Postal Workers Union in 1971, after taking a leading role in the hard-fought national strike of postal workers in 1970. Under the dynamic presidencies of Moe Biller and Josie MacMillan from the 1958 through the 1980s, the local won significant gains for its members. Both the membership and the local union leadership became more diverse as post office jobs opened up to minorities and women as a result of civil rights initiatives of the 1960s.
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes minutes, administrative files, officers files, stewards files, bargaining files, grievances, affiliates files, publications of the local, reports, financial records, subject files and ephemera.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Metro Area Postal Union Oral History Collection (OH 3)
New York Metro Area Postal Union Photographs (PHOTOS 11)
American Postal Workers Union: Moe Biller Files (WAG 99)
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the New York Metro Area Postal Union, 1980. The accession number associated with this gift is 1950.053.
Postal service |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.; Postal Strike, U.S., 1970.; Postal service |x Employees.; Postal service -- Employees -- Labor unions; United States Postal Service |x Employees |x History.; United States Postal Service; Biller, Moe, 1915-2003; MacMillan, Josie; National Federation of Post Office Clerks. Local 10 (New York, N.Y.); New York Metro Area Postal Union; Manhattan-Bronx Postal Union; Postal Union of Manhattan-Bronx Clerks; New York Metro Area Postal Union
- New York Federation of Post Office Clerks Newsletter: officer lists, sports quiz submissions, postal press association award certificates, federation credit union, interview with 1st Local 10 President Albert Rossdale, Audit Committee Reports: hospital plan, Constitution and Bylaws; Election Materials, Tax and Financial Records 1943-1959 (Box 1)
- Minutes: Board of Officers, Executive Board, Membership Committee 1959-1976 (Box 2)
- Constitutions, Finance Insurance Fund Records: correspondence, board of trustee meeting minutes, audit reports, Credit Union Records: forms, audit reports, membership drives, NY State information, President Moe Biller Records 1958-1978 (Box 3)
  - President Moe Biller Records: Kingsbridge-correspondences and press releases regarding July 1969 Bronx postal employees walkout (Box 3)
- President Moe Biller Records: 1952-1977 (Box 4)
  - 1970 Postal Strike and Reform-correspondence, reports, news releases, clippings, congressional testimony, Biller's diary of events and chronology of strike (Box 4)
  - Brooklyn Museum postal workers exhibit proposal; Constitutional Amendments; 1971 House hearing testimony (Box 4)
- President Moe Biller Records: 1965-1974 (Box 5)
  - 1966 and 1967 Mail handlers Election, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - Poor Mail Service-clippings, articles, interview transcripts (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Robert F. Kennedy (Box 5)
  - MBPU Credit Union (Box 5)
  - Cornell Urban Affairs Program (Box 5)
  - NPU-UFPC Merger: materials on structure and constitution (Box 5)
  - Postal Reform-clippings and press releases (Box 5)
- President Moe Biller Records: 1953-1974 (Box 6)
  - Notes on NY Metro History; Study of factors that influence fatigue in letter sorters (Box 6)
  - NYPO seniority directives (Box 6)
  - Udall Committee testimony (Box 6)
  - Correspondence with Congressional Representatives (Box 6)
  - National Bulk Mail Service Information (Box 6)
  - American Postal Workers Union-National Association of Letter Carriers Merger (Box 6)
  - Dues Request Letters; Letters to Congressional Reps and Senators concerning Brooklyn Army Terminal (Box 6)
  - 1972 Regional Impasse (Box 6)
  - National Association of Letter Carriers Branch 36 Elections material (Box 6)
  - NPU National Convention-1962, 1968, and 1970, 1962, 1968, 1970 (Box 6)
  - 1972 Hiring Freeze: articles, correspondence, directives and press releases (Box 6)
  - Local Mergers-1971 (Box 6)
  - Letter from Secretary Of Labor-re: payroll deductions for union dues-1963 (Box 6)
  - Paper on history of New York Post Office underground pneumatic tube system (Box 6)
  - Equal Opportunity/Anti-Discrimination-1962-1965 (Box 6)
  - UFPC-NPU Merger Negotiations 1964-1969 (Box 6)
- President Moe Biller Records and President Josie McMilliam Records 1960-1980 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence with individuals, 1978-1979 (Box 7)
  - Post Master General Gag Order-re: Congressional Contracts 1971: letters, news flashes and directives (Box 7)
  - Constitutions-national and state (Box 7)
  - Senator Jacob Javits-correspondence 1960-1974 (Box 7)
  - Senator Charles Goodell-correspondence 1970 (Box 7)
  - Installation of Officers 1962-1966: meeting notices, Biller speeches and committee reports (Box 7)
  - New York City Financial Crisis: correspondence with members, clippings and Biller open letter to President Ford (Box 7)
  - American Postal Workers Union President Filbey: correspondence, news flashes and announcement of death/replacement (Box 7)
  - American Postal Workers Union Elections (Box 7)
  - Nixon Pardon materials (Box 7)
  - MBPU Community Services Referral Program: correspondence with Post Master General and Legislators (Box 7)
  - Biller 1973 testimony before House Postal Service Sub-Committee (Box 7)
  - Correspondence re: aborted July 1971 strike (Box 7)
  - United Way-Combined Federal campaign: correspondence, brochures and reports (Box 7)
  - 1974 "Battle of the Bulk": correspondence, mail studies, meeting summaries, new flashes, clippings and job postings (Box 7)
  - Clippings from Jewish Daily Forward (Yiddish)-re: Biller election to American Postal Workers Union President 1980 (Box 7)
  - President Josie McMilliam Records: clippings on election; Women's March for Equality (Box 7)
  - President Josie McMilliam Records: radio appearance-November 1980 (Box 7)
- Legislative Director Eleanor Bailey Records, Executive Board Files, Stewards Files 1959-1981 (Box 8)
  - Drafts of speeches and articles; Report on Legislation (Box 8)
  - Correspondence; Political Materials: Congresswoman Bella Abzug, Senator Jacob Javits, League of Women Voters (Box 8)
  - Community Service Committee: social service and union programs, 1976 convention legislative committee reports and notes (Box 8)
  - American Postal Workers Union Human Relations Department (Box 8)
  - American Cancer Society materials (Box 8)
  - League of Women Voters ERA kits (Box 8)
  - ERA, Coaltition of Labor Union Women and International Year of the Woman material-1975 (Box 8)
  - Certificate from Labor Studies Center (Box 8)
  - Executive Board Files: 1977 List of Executive Board Members (Box 8)
  - Executive Board Files: Meeting Attendance: letters to encourage attendance, MBPU special letters to delegates 1961-1999 (Box 8)
  - Executive Board Files: Notes on various New York Metro Officers (Box 8)
  - Stewards Files:NYB and FMC 1977 Elections: Ballots and Tallies, election rules, candidate correspondence (Box 8)
  - Stewards Files: 1976 Elections: correspondence from prospective candidates (Box 8)
  - Stewards Files: 1976-1977 Motor Vehicle Elections: ballots and tallies (Box 8)
  - Stewards Files: 1974 Elections: correspondence, sample ballots and results (Box 8)
  - Stewards Files: American Postal Workers Union Manual: A Textbook for Postal Stewards-1980, Guidelines for Stewards: Grievance Procedures-1973-74, 1975-78, 1978-81, 1973-1981 (Box 8)
- Stewards Files, Contract Negotiations Records, 1963-1964 Files, 1963-1978 (Box 9)
  - Stewards Files: ZMT Part-Time Flexis request for steward: notices, correspondence and List of employees (Box 9)
  - Stewards Files: Correspondence between Biller and Stewards-1970-1978; Stewards Dinner-1975-1976 (Box 9)
  - Stewards Files: NYSSILR-Cornell: Teaching Manual on the Steward and the grievance procedure and course outline; Resignations and correspondence 1975-1976 (Box 9)
  - Stewards Files: Orientation Packet-1972 (Box 9)
  - Stewards Files: Pre-1972 Stewards Manual (Box 9)
  - Stewards Files: 1978 New Steward Packet: forms and booklets (Box 9)
  - Stewards Files: Stewards Elections: Ballots, and tallies-1978, 1977, 1976, 1976-1978 (Box 9)
  - Contract Negotiations Records: (material is grouped by years of contract. Within each contract period, printed contracts are placed first, followed by national and then local negotiating material) (Box 9)
  - 1963-1964:Agreement between United States Post Office Department and UFPC, NACL, NAPO and GSME, NASDM, NFPOMVE and National Rural Letter Carriers Association (Box 9)
  - 1963-1964: Contract between NYPO and National Association of Letter Carriers #36, NFPOMVE #2 and MBPU-July 14, 1963: includes supplements for clerks, mobile, mail handlers and maintenance (Box 9)
  - 1963-1964: NYPO and MBPU: Maintenance supplement (Box 9)
  - 1963-1964: NYPO Contract Negotiations (Box 9)
  - 1963-1964: Contract implementation-Local: various materials (Box 9)
  - 1963-1964: NYPO with MBPU, National Association of Letter Carriers #36, NFPOMVE #2-1963: local negotiation material-Puerto Rico, Jamaica, Brooklyn Post Office (Box 9)
  - 1963-1964: Local: Union recognition, invalidation, correspondence and memos (Box 9)
  - 1963-1964: Bronx Post Office Motor Vehicle and mail handler supplements with MBPU (Box 9)
- Contract Negotiations Records:1964-1970 (Box 10)
  - Agreement between United States Post Office Department and UFPC, National Association of Letter Carriers, NAPO and GSME, NASDM, NFPOMVE and National Rural Letter Carriers Association-July 1, 1964-October 31, 1965: printed (one copy annotated) includes relevant clippings from postal bulletin (Box 10)
  - Postal Bulletin-June 32, 1965: interpretation of 1964 national agreement, June 1965 (Box 10)
  - Procedures for local regognition and negotiation: with memos from NPU- June 1965, September 1966 (Box 10)
  - Mailhandler Election, National-1964: on recognition (Box 10)
  - Agreement between Post Office Bronx New York and National Association of Letter Carriers #36 and MBPU eff. October 1, 1964 (Box 10)
  - Basic Supplementary Bronx contracts for 1964-1965: Bronx Post Office, MBPU and National Association of Letter Carriers #36 (Box 10)
  - Bronx Post Office contract negotiations-1964 (Box 10)
  - Agreement between New York, NYPO and National Association of Letter Carriers #36 and MBPU: October 10, 1964-October 31, 1965 (Box 10)
  - Bronx Post Office-October 10, 1964-October 31, 1965: negotiation materials and drafts (Box 10)
  - Bronx Post Office Basic-1964-1965: proposed contract (Box 10)
  - Supplemental Contract between Bronx Post Office and MBPU for clerks-1964-1965: drafts (Box 10)
  - Contracts with NYPO-October 1964-October 1965 (Box 10)
  - NYPO and MBPU, National Association of Letter Carriers and NFPOMVE #2-1964 (Box 10)
  - Proposals for local contract-1964: correspondence (Box 10)
  - NYPO Contract May 18, 1965-October 31, 1965: defined work areas at terminal points, correspondence and complaints (Box 10)
  - Related publication-Post Office Department, New York Region: Employee-Management Negotiations Procedures and Techniques July 1964 (Box 10)
  - Motor Vehicle representation election-November 13-November 20, 1965 (Box 10)
  - Impasses, NYPO and Bronx, 1966 (Box 10)
  - Related publication: Cullen, Donald-Negotiating Labor-Management Contracts, Bulletin 56, NYSSILR-Cornell-September 1965 (Box 10)
  - Agreement between United States Post Office Department and National Association of Letter Carriers, NAPO and GSME, mailhandlers, NASDM, NFPOMVE, NRLCA, UFPC-September 24, 1966-October 31, 1967 (Box 10)
  - Agreement between United States Post Office Department and UFPC-signed August 31, 1966, eff. To October 31, 1967, August 31, 1966-October 31,1967 (Box 10)
  - 1964 and 1966 Agreements between Post Office Department and 7 Employee Organizations holding exclusive recognition, with explanation of changes: September 24, 1966 (Box 10)
  - Postal Bulletin, Special Issue, May 5, 1967 "Interpretation of 1964 and 1966 National Agreements" (Box 10)
  - Agreement between NYPO and National Association of Letter Carriers #36, MBPU, NFPOMVE #92, March 28, 1967-October 31, 1967 (Box 10)
  - Agreement between Bronx Post Office and National Association of Letter Carriers #36 and MBPU, January 31, 1967-October 31, 1967 (Box 10)
  - Excerpts from "Local Agreement between Post Office, Bronx, and National Postal Union, MBPU" for mailhandlers, eff. January 31, 1967- October 31, 1967 (Box 10)
  - Local negotiations-1966: preliminary material and suggestions (Box 10)
  - NYPO contracts-1966-1967 (Box 10)
  - Bronx Post Office agreement with MBP, National Association of Letter Carriers #36 and NFPOMVE #2-1966 (Box 10)
  - Local-Other locals of NPU: Pittsburgh Post Office and Pittsburgh Postal Union for Maintenance, May 12, 1967-October 31, 1967 (Box 10)
  - Background research material: Developments in Public Service Labor Relations-A one-day conference conducted by NYSSILR-Cornell, May 12, 1966 (Box 10)
  - Agreement between United States Post Office Department and National Association of Letter Carriers, NAPO and GSME, mailhandlers, NASDM, NFPOMVE, NRLCA, UFPC: March 9, 1968-March 8, 1970 (Box 10)
  - Impasses: agreed to with region-Albertson, Hempstead, Maserna, Hicksville, Port Jefferson Station, Rockville Center, Valley Stream and Westbury, 1968-1969 (Box 10)
  - NPU Local Negotiations work seminar, March 16-March 17, 1968 (Box 10)
  - Impasses: Jamaica-1968 (Box 10)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1968-1973 (Box 11)
  - Impasses, 1968-1969: agreed to in region, Washington, Jamaica (Box 11)
  - Local agreements: other locals of NPU in New York State and Puerto Rico (Box 11)
  - Bronx Local Agreements, 1968: Basic and Supplementary (Box 11)
  - NYPO contracts and non-negotiable items, 1968 (Box 11)
  - Mailhandlers report and negotiating material, NYPO-June 1968 (also includes supplemental contract for mailhandlers of New York Post Office Department and MBPU, July 1963-March 1964, July 1963-June 1968 (Box 11)
  - Proposed mailhandler contract, NYPO June 12, 1968 (Box 11)
  - Local agreement between Bronx Post Office and National Association of Letter Carriers #36, MBPU and Mailhandlers #203, June 10, 1968-March 8, 1970 (Box 11)
  - Local agreement between NYPO and National Association of Letter Carriers #36, MBPU, NFPOMVE #2, March 8, 1970 (Box 11)
  - Brooklyn Post Office-Local union agreement contracts wth National Association of Letter Carriers #41, March 8, 1970 (Box 11)
  - Brooklyn Postal Union-clerical, NASDM 962, Mailhandlers #39, motor vehicle (Box 11)
  - Local agreement between Bronx Post Office and National Association of Letter Carriers 436, MBPU and Mailhandlers #203, June 6, 1968-March 8, 1970 (Box 11)
  - Local contract preparation-1968 (Box 11)
  - Bulletin Board Seminars-"Manhattan-Bronx Postal University" on local contract-1968 (Box 11)
  - Local agreement between Bronx Post Office and National Association of Letter Carriers #36, MBPU and Mailhandlers #203, June 10, 1968-March 8, 1970 (Box 11)
  - NYPO-Basic and supplemental memos of understanding (Box 11)
  - National Agreement-comparison of 1968-1970 agreement with 1966-1967 agreement, 1966-1970 (Box 11)
  - National Collective Bargaining Agreement: United States Postal Service and American Postal Workers Union, July 20, 1971-July 20, 1973 (Box 11)
  - Working text: 1971 National agreement, United States Postal Service and National Association of Letter Carriers, NAPOGSME, NASDM, NFPOMVE, NRLCA, UFPC, Mailhandlers, July 20, 1971-July 20, 1973 (Box 11)
  - American Postal Worker, Special Edition, May 1972, National Agreement between American Postal Workers Union and United States Postal Service, 1971-1973 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, contract orientation booklet, notes and memos, 1970 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence by Biller, copy of contract, postal bulletins and related material for 1971-1973 American Postal Workers Union contract negotiations material, 1971-1973 (Box 11)
  - Impasses, local-1972 (Box 11)
  - Local memos: proposals and interpretation meetings, 1972 (Box 11)
  - Bronx Post Office-Mailhandlers supplemental to memo of agreement, 1972 (Box 11)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1971-1975 (Box 12)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1973-1975 (Box 13)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1973-1978 (Box 14)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1975-1981 (Box 15)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1960-1979 (Box 16)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1963-1974 (Box 17)
- Contract Negotiations Records:1962-1980 (Box 18)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1962-1980 (Box 19)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1964-1979 (Box 20)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1975-1980 (Box 21)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1956-1980 (Box 22)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1956-1980 (Box 23)
- Contract Negotiations Records: 1957-1979 (Box 24)
- Arbitration Cases: 1978 (Box 25)
- Arbitration Cases: Local Units NYPO and Meadows: snowstorm-Administrative leave cases (certified for arbitration), 1978 (Box 26)
- Arbitration Cases: Local Units Meadows: snowstorm-Administrative leave cases (certified for arbitration), 1978 (Box 27)
- Local: 1968-1976 (Box 28)
- Local: 1972-1977 (Box 29)
- Local: 1966-1973 (Box 30)
- Local:1969-1973 (Box 31)
- Local: 1959-1973 (Box 32)
- Local: 1967-1973 (Box 33)
- Local: 1970-1977 (Box 34)
- Local: 1963-1975 (Box 35)
- Local: 1961-1978 (Box 36)
- Local: 1970-1978 (Box 37)
- Local: 1972-1976 (Box 38)
- Local: 1969-1975 and Arbitration Materials (Box 39)
- Local: 1962-1979 and Local-Individuals (Box 40)
- Local-Individuals and Arbitrations, 1970-1978 (Box 41)
- Arbitrations: 1958-1981 (Box 42)
- Arbitrations: 1958-1980 (Box 43)
- Arbitrations: 1967-1980 (Box 44)
- Regional and Counsel Files-Court Cases, 1948-1977 (Box 45)
- General Subject Files: 1953-1979 (Box 46)
- General Subject Files: 1961-1979 (Box 47)
- General Subject Files: 1968-1980 (Box 48)
- General Subject Files: 1953-1980 (Box 49)
- General Subject Files: 1961-1980 (Box 50)
- General Subject Files: 1955-1979 (Box 51)
- General Subject Files: 1964-1974 (Box 52)
- General Subject Files: 1963-1979 (Box 53)
- General Subject Files: 1959-1980 (Box 54)
- General Subject Files: 1961-1967 (Box 55)
- General Subject Files: 1960-1980 (Box 56)
- General Subject Files: 1957-1980 (Box 57)
- Women and the Postal Service Files: 1932-1980 (Box 58)
- Motor Vehicles Division Records and the Union Mail Office Files, 1939-1978 (Box 59)
- Affiliates Records: 1910-1973 (Box 60)
- Affiliates Records: 1959-1966 (Box 61)
- Affiliates Records: 1959-1972 (Box 62)
- Affiliates Records: 1962-1969 (Box 63)
- Affiliates Records: 1962-1979 (Box 64)
- Affiliates Records: 1975-1979 (Box 65)
- Affiliates Records: 1971-1979 (Box 66)
- Affiliates Records: 1971-1975 (Box 67)
- Affiliates Records: 1961-1973 (Box 68)
- Affiliates Records: 1960-1973 (Box 69)
- Affiliates Records: 1941-1980 (Box 70)
- Affiliates Records and Management-United States Postal Service, 1946-1979 (Box 71)
- Management-United States Postal Service, 1962-1979 (Box 72)
- Management-United States Postal Service, 1955-1980 (Box 73)
- News Flashes, Bulletins, Reports and News Services: 1957-1964 (Box 74)
- News Flashes, Bulletins, Reports and News Services: 1965-1968 (Box 75)
- News Flashes, Bulletins, Reports and News Services: 1969-1976 (Box 76)
- News Flashes, Bulletins, Reports and News Services: 1943-1980 (Box 77)
- News Flashes, Bulletins, Reports and News Services: 1959-1971 (Box 78)
- News Flashes, Bulletins, Reports and News Services: 1971-1980 (Box 79)
- News Flashes, Bulletins, Reports and News Services: 1949-1980 (Box 80)
- Archived Website, Nov 1, 2013-ongoing
  Scope and Content Note
  The New York Metro Area Postal Union (American Postal Workers Union, Local 10) represents clerks, motor vehicle staff, maintenance workers and mail-handlers in the greater New York City area. In 1973 the union changed its name to the New York Metro Area Postal Union, from the Postal Union of Manhattan-Bronx Clerks, the new name reflecting the inclusion of the New York Bulk and Foreign Mail Center and the North Jersey Facility in the local's bargaining unit. The website contains news listings, their health plan, agreements, and other materials.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
- Unprocessed Posters and Scrapbook (Box 81)